<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jeybird248.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jeybird248.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-12T00:05:52+00:00</updated><id>https://jeybird248.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Reflection: It Builds Character but</title><link href="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2025/maturity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection: It Builds Character but"/><published>2025-02-10T02:48:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-10T02:48:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2025/maturity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2025/maturity/"><![CDATA[<p>Maturity is often framed as a trifecta: biological, emotional, and psychological. Biologically, it’s about your body and brain catching up with the calendar. Emotional maturity? That’s when you can keep your cool even when someone cuts you off in traffic. Psychological maturity? It’s the ability to see beyond yourself—like realizing that maybe, just maybe, the world doesn’t revolve around your Spotify playlist.</p> <h2 id="the-early-days-of-maturity">The Early Days of “Maturity”</h2> <p>I can’t remember the first time someone told me I was mature for my age, but I do remember how it felt. Like I’d unlocked some secret level of adulthood that other kids my age couldn’t even fathom. Like winning an Oscar for Best Child Actor in the Drama of Life. While my classmates were busy arguing over whose Pokémon cards were cooler, I was sitting at the adult table, nodding along to conversations about mortgage rates and the price of gas. Not because I understood any of it—God no—but because it felt safer there. Kids my age were unpredictable, sometimes cruel. Adults, on the other hand? They liked me because I was quiet, polite, and didn’t cause trouble. I was their dream child—an old soul in a pint-sized body.</p> <p>But here’s the thing about being an “old soul”: it’s lonely as hell. Sure, the adults liked me, but they were also <em>adults</em>. They weren’t going to invite me to play tag or trade snacks at recess. And the kids? They thought I was weird. Too serious. Too quiet. Too… something, I guess. So there I was, stuck in this no-man’s-land between childhood and whatever comes after. Really puts being a ‘young adult’ into perspective.</p> <h2 id="the-teenage-medal-of-maturity">The Teenage Medal of Maturity</h2> <p>By the time I hit my teenage years, being called mature for my age started to feel less like a compliment and more like a challenge. It wasn’t just about being well-behaved anymore; it was about living up to this image of myself as someone who had it all together. And let me tell you, keeping up that façade is exhausting.</p> <p>Take high school, for example. While my friends were sneaking out to parties or stressing over prom dates, I was busy being <em>the responsible one</em>. The one who gave advice, who stayed sober so everyone else could get drunk without worrying about how they’d get home. And yeah, part of me took pride in that role—it felt good to be needed. But another part of me just wanted to scream: <em>Can someone else be the adult for once?</em></p> <h2 id="the-ugly-truth-about-mature-for-your-age">The Ugly Truth About “Mature for Your Age”</h2> <p>Here’s the uncomfortable truth: trauma has a way of fast-tracking maturity. For me, it started when my family plopped me down in a country where I didn’t speak the language or understand the culture. To make things worse, they didn’t either. Suddenly, I wasn’t just a kid anymore. I was an interpreter, a mediator, a problem-solver. Childhood wasn’t something I lived; it was something I left behind, and never had the liberty to pick back up.</p> <p>Maybe you were forced into adulthood too soon. Maybe life gave you more funerals than birthday parties. Whatever the case, this so-called “maturity” often comes from enduring what no child—or adolescent—should have to. You get so used to being the bridge between worlds that you forget you were supposed to have solid ground of your own. Every conversation, every decision, every moment of uncertainty—you smooth it over, make it easier for everyone else. And in the process, you learn to shrink, to silence your own needs, because there’s never room for them when you’re too busy holding everything together.</p> <p>Then one day, you look around and realize you don’t even know what it feels like to exist without carrying someone else’s weight. Being labeled “mature” doesn’t sound like a compliment anymore, does it?</p> <h2 id="the-turning-point">The Turning Point</h2> <p>Now I’m 21 for some reason, and maturity is a reminder of everything I’ve been through to get here. It’s not something I wear with pride anymore; it’s something I carry with weariness. Because if there’s one thing I’ve learned, it’s that maturity isn’t always earned—it’s often forced upon you by circumstances beyond your control.</p> <p>And honestly? If I could go back and trade some of that maturity for a little more ignorance—a few more years of blind, uncomplicated joy—I would. Not because I don’t value what I’ve learned, but because some lessons come at too high a cost.</p> <h2 id="what-maturity-really-means">What Maturity Really Means</h2> <p>Maturity is often mistaken for composure, responsibility, or the ability to shoulder burdens without complaint. But at its core, it’s about perspective—about understanding yourself and the world in a way that makes sense of past and present.</p> <p>But perspective is a double-edged sword. Sometimes it’s a gift, letting you see beyond yourself, helping you make sense of others. Other times, it’s a weight—one that distances you from the people around you, makes innocence feel like a language you can no longer speak. There are things you can only see because you don’t know any better—like believing in Santa Claus or thinking your high school crush is your soulmate.</p> <p>When we label kids as “mature,” we risk robbing them of those blissfully ignorant moments. Instead of encouraging them to explore and make mistakes, we saddle them with expectations they didn’t ask for and probably can’t meet without sacrificing some part of their innocence until one day, they wake up and realize they’ve spent more time being “grown” than just being.</p> <p>So if you ever meet someone who seems mature for their age, don’t just applaud them for it. Ask them how they’re really doing—because chances are, they’ve been carrying more than their fair share of weight for far too long. To let them explore without fear of judgment. To make mistakes without feeling like they’re letting everyone down.</p> <p>And if you’re someone who’s been labeled “mature” your whole life? Take it from me: it’s okay to put down the armor every once in a while. To let yourself be messy and vulnerable and human. Because maturity isn’t about having all the answers—it’s about knowing when it’s okay not to have them at all.</p> <p>So here’s to unlearning what we thought we knew about maturity, to giving ourselves permission to be—messy, reckless, human. And maybe find some joy in the process.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Because you can look back but you can't go back]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Opinion: Escapsim, Complacency, and the Inner Gigachad</title><link href="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2025/escapism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opinion: Escapsim, Complacency, and the Inner Gigachad"/><published>2025-01-21T02:48:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-21T02:48:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2025/escapism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2025/escapism/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="from-zero-to-hero-why-were-all-rooting-for-losers-these-days">From Zero to Hero: Why We’re All Rooting for Losers These Days</h2> <p>Once upon a time, our heroes were untouchable. They wore tuxedos to gunfights, jumped off skyscrapers without breaking a sweat, or wielded powers that made gods look underwhelming. They were motivators, idols to look up to and follow. But lately, something strange has happened. Our protagonists are no longer the flawless paragons we once idolized. Instead, they’re… well, losers. Struggling moms saving the multiverse, high schooler turned edgy anti-hero, or socially awkward anime girls that can only communicate through a flipbook. What’s going on here? Have we collectively decided that being cool is overrated?</p> <p>The answer lies somewhere between societal disillusionment and a desperate need for escapism. In a world where economic stagnation and social pressures weigh heavy, it seems we’ve traded in our aspirational fantasies for something more relatable—flawed characters who stumble their way to greatness. But is this shift empowering, or are we just fooling ourselves with prettier versions of mediocrity?</p> <h2 id="why-we-love-watching-nobodies-become-somebodies">Why We Love Watching Nobodies Become Somebodies</h2> <p>Let’s talk about <em>isekai</em>. If you’re not familiar, it’s a genre of Japanese storytelling where characters are whisked away to another world (think <em>The Matrix</em> but with more swords and badly written existential crises). These stories thrive on one simple premise: losers get second chances. Whether it’s the socially inept gamer who becomes an overpowered hero or the book-obsessed-psychopath who manages to razzle-dazzle medieval peasants with modern knowledge, isekai offers the ultimate fantasy—escaping your current life and starting over as someone extraordinary.</p> <p>And it’s not just Japan. Western media loves this trope too. Remember <em>Ready Player One</em>? A broke, awkward kid saves the virtual universe because he knows obscure trivia about 80s pop culture. Or how about <em>Harry Potter</em>, unloved, downtrodden boy living under the stairs discovers he’s actually a wizard destined to defeat the most feared dark lord in history? These stories resonate because they tap into a universal longing: the hope that maybe, just maybe, we’re destined for something greater than our boring, underwhelming lives.</p> <p>But here’s the catch—these narratives often cheat. The protagonist doesn’t succeed because they work hard or grow as a person; they succeed because they’re “chosen” or stumble upon godlike powers. It’s escapism at its finest but also its most dangerous.</p> <h2 id="when-escapism-becomes-a-trap">When Escapism Becomes a Trap</h2> <p>On the surface, these stories seem empowering—they tell us that even the most flawed among us can achieve greatness. But dig a little deeper, and you’ll notice a troubling pattern: many of these narratives romanticize passivity.</p> <p>Take isekai again. The protagonist is usually handed immense power without earning it. One minute they’re a nobody; the next, they’re fighting off zombies or saving the world from some guy with a hand fetish. Sure, it’s fun to watch, but what message does it send? That greatness doesn’t require effort? That you just need to wait for some magical Deus ex machina to fix your life?</p> <p>Even outside of fantasy, this trend persists. Modern media often glorifies “acceptance” in ways that border on complacency. Characters are celebrated for “being themselves,” but rarely are they challenged to grow or change in meaningful ways. The worst offender of this is the growing trend of “romance with a gimmick” shows that decided that drama and actually building upto a relationship took too long and instead opted for the same Girl A with a quirk meets Boy A and they live happily ever after. It’s as if we’ve collectively decided that striving for something in life was too much work.</p> <p>And maybe that’s the point. In a world where real-life challenges feel insurmountable—crippling student debt, climate change, political chaos—it’s no wonder we gravitate toward stories that let us off the hook. But while escapism provides temporary relief, it also risks widening the gap between reality and expectations.</p> <h2 id="the-case-for-struggle-why-we-might-need-to-suffer">The Case for Struggle: Why We Might Need to Suffer</h2> <p>Here’s an uncomfortable truth: growth requires discomfort. No amount of magical thinking or escapist fantasies can replace the value of hard work and perseverance. And deep down, we know this. It’s why stories like <em>Rocky</em> or <em>Good Will Hunting</em> still resonate—they remind us that greatness isn’t handed out; it’s earned through struggle.</p> <p>So how do we reconcile this with our love for loser-to-hero narratives? By rethinking what “acceptance” really means. True acceptance isn’t about resigning yourself to mediocrity; it’s about acknowledging where you are while striving to become better.</p> <p>Imagine if media leaned into this idea—flawed characters who don’t just stumble into success but actively work for it. Imagine an isekai where the protagonist doesn’t gain instant godlike powers but has to learn and grow alongside their new world. Imagine stories that inspire us not by showing us what we could be if circumstances were different but by showing us what we could become if we tried. How we can go even further beyond.</p> <h2 id="unleashing-your-inner-gigachad">Unleashing Your Inner Gigachad</h2> <p>Let me introduce you to Korea’s first viral meme of 2025: the Inner Gigachad. What started as a joke about embracing absurd confidence when the world seemed to be burning around us quickly became a rallying cry for self-improvement. People plastered a mixture of broken English and Korean glued together with pure charisma and confidence across their social media feeds, paired with images of chiseled figures captioned with lines like, “Hey 만삣삐, you have to trust yourself to take action. Only you can decide what the right decision is.”</p> <p>It was ridiculous. It was over-the-top. But it worked. The <em>Inner Gigachad</em> wasn’t about actually being perfect—it was about channeling an audacious belief in yourself, even when you felt like a total loser. It was about showing up for life with the same swagger as someone who thinks they’re invincible, even if you’re barely holding it together.</p> <p>So maybe you’re not destined to save the multiverse or lead a rebellion against a dystopian regime. Maybe your story is smaller—quieter—but no less heroic. Whether it’s learning a new skill, mending a broken relationship, or simply getting out of bed when everything feels impossible, these are the battles that define us. So STOP 띵킹 만삣삐, a day will come where your hard work is rewarded, not by some benevolent hand-waving god, but by you yourself.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Because sometimes you need the stick more than the carrot]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Opinion: The Problem with ‘Positivity Culture’</title><link href="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/positivity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opinion: The Problem with ‘Positivity Culture’"/><published>2024-11-28T02:48:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-28T02:48:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/positivity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/positivity/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-future-is-not-bright-the-toxic-positivity-trap-in-a-doomer-world">The Future is (Not) Bright: The Toxic Positivity Trap in a Doomer World</h2> <p>It’s 2024, and the future’s looking grim, right? The world’s on fire (literally), climate change is only trending more frequently, and your dream job in tech has become some kind of corporate hostage situation where the hostages are your self-esteem and hope for any future career. The game is rigged, and the stakes are high. But hey—stay positive, right? If you’re not projecting an image of perfect, sunshine-filled happiness, are you even trying to make it in this cruel world?</p> <p>Here we are, caught in a paradox. On one hand, you’ve got a generation of doomers who are hell-bent on telling everyone how bleak and hopeless things are (thanks, Zoomers). On the other, there’s the ever-growing force of toxic positivity trying to “fix” the world with a hashtag and a wellness retreat.</p> <p>Guess what? Neither side has the answer.</p> <h2 id="doomer-culture-why-the-kids-are-all-rightbut-also-theyre-not">Doomer Culture: Why the Kids Are All Right—But Also, They’re Not</h2> <p>If you spend five minutes on Twitter (now called X for whatever reason), you’ll see Gen Z and Alpha doing what they do best: predicting the end of the world in real-time. They’ve inherited a planet that’s boiling under its own weight, a job market that treats them like a joke, and an economy that makes “getting by” seem like an unattainable goal. They’ve been gaslighted by an entire generation before them, and now they’re collectively shaking their heads while waiting for it all to implode.</p> <p>So, yeah, it makes sense that they’re living in a perpetual state of existential crisis. How could you not when the world keeps promising <em>solutions</em> that turn out to be nothing more than slicked-up scams and all the people making decisions are all old men that look like they would communicate through morse code using the clattering of their loose dentures? Here’s the thing: doomers have a point. They are right to be skeptical about a system that only seems to reward the already privileged, and the job market? Good luck finding anything other than a soul-crushing, self-esteem-destroying minefield.</p> <p>Take the tech industry, for example. The opportunities are endless! But so are the fake job postings. Companies figured out the “FREE MONEY HACK” that people have been searching for like the One Piece for decades: post listings for jobs that don’t exist to rack up free tax credits, it’s like some dystopian version of corporate charity. And if you somehow manage to get an interview? Don’t be surprised if you’re ghosted for weeks, only to get a call at 3 p.m. on a Friday asking you if you have 5+ years of experience for an entry-level position. And if somehow they haven’t hung up on you, by the third question it’ll be <em>you</em> that’s waiting to get off the line. These interviewers don’t even know what job they’re hiring for half the time; they’re just reading off a script, pretending that “What’s your greatest weakness?” is a valid question for an actual grown-up.</p> <p>I get it, doomers. It’s hard to stay optimistic when you’re navigating a system that seems built to make you fail. But here’s the thing—this negativity, as valid as it feels in the moment, is just creating a toxic echo chamber. If everyone’s stuck in this “we’re doomed” spiral, how are we ever going to get out of it? The system may suck, but <em>not</em> trying to change it doesn’t do anyone any good.</p> <h2 id="toxic-positivity-good-vibes-only-for-the-already-privileged">Toxic Positivity: “Good Vibes Only” for the Already Privileged</h2> <p>Enter the opposite end of the spectrum: toxic positivity. It’s everywhere, and it’s always lurking, waiting to convince you that all your problems could be solved with a little more “positive thinking” and “good vibes hehe XD.”</p> <p>Listen, positivity isn’t the problem here. I love positivity. I could have it for breakfast, lunch, and dinner. The problem is pretending that if we all just slap a smile on our faces and tell ourselves “everything will be okay,” the world will magically shift into some pristine version of itself. But here’s the thing—pretending everything is okay when it’s not doesn’t help anyone. In fact, it actively makes things worse.</p> <p>You’re struggling. <em>I’m</em> struggling. Littly Timmy down the street at the age of 4 is struggling. But you’re expected to act like you’re on a permanent vacation with crystal-clear waters and a sunset view. You can’t let anyone see that you’re stressed, tired, or lost. Why? Because people won’t care, and worse, they’ll use it against you. This is especially true in Korean culture, where every single interaction seems to be scrutinized by others, and showing any sign of vulnerability is treated like an admission of failure. Keep your emotions bottled up. Keep the facade intact. Smile, post your filtered selfies that probably wouldn’t even pass the FaceID test, and pray your self-doubt doesn’t catch up with you.</p> <p>But when you’re forced to act like you’re “fine” all the time, there’s no room to be real. No room for vulnerability. No room to say, “I’m struggling, and that’s okay.” Instead, you get trapped in an endless cycle of “good vibes only :))” mantras that do nothing but feed your feelings of inadequacy.</p> <p>Let’s face it: The wellness industry doesn’t have the answers. More yoga poses and motivational quotes won’t fix a broken system. If anything, they just gloss over the real issues, making you feel worse when you realize that no amount of “positivity” can make a toxic job market or the pressures of society go away.</p> <h2 id="the-echo-chamber-of-negativity">The Echo Chamber of Negativity</h2> <p>This is where the doomers and the “good vibes” people come together—not in harmony, but in the dark vortex of negativity. Turns out, negative numbers don’t always cancel out. As everyone falls into their own echo chambers, they start validating each other’s worst fears. Doomers validate each other’s apocalyptic views with memes about how we’re all doomed to drown in student debt and climate change. The positivity crowd validates each other’s rejection of reality with hashtags about manifesting good energy and success.</p> <p>And what’s the endgame here? The negativity that the doomers spread only gets worse when they’re surrounded by other people who share their fears. Meanwhile, the “good vibes” crowd’s refusal to acknowledge reality makes everyone feel like they’re missing something—like maybe they’re the ones doing it wrong.</p> <p>Both sides are missing the point. The answer isn’t either/or. It’s a messy, ugly “both.”</p> <h2 id="youre-struggling-im-struggling-were-all-strugglingand-thats-okay">You’re Struggling, I’m Struggling, We’re All Struggling—And That’s Okay</h2> <p>Here’s the unvarnished truth: life isn’t going to be perfect. No amount of positive thinking will change the fact that the system is broken. The job market is broken. And yeah, your social media posts? They’re not changing that either. We all have our moments of struggle, whether it’s in our career, personal lives, or even just navigating a society that feels like it was built to make us fail.</p> <p>The trick is not to pretend it’s all sunshine and rainbows when it’s clearly not. Embrace the pain. Embrace the struggle. The idea that we can fix everything with good vibes is toxic because it keeps us from dealing with the root problems. You can’t heal if you’re not willing to face what’s wrong. You can’t fix the system if you’re too busy pretending it’s all working out.</p> <p>In the end, maybe we should all take a page out of <em>Inside Out</em>—<em>not</em> the “happiness is everything” page, but the one that shows how Sadness, Anger, and Fear are just as vital as Joy. They all have a role to play in who we are and how we navigate the world.</p> <h2 id="final-thoughts-authenticity-over-positivity">Final Thoughts: Authenticity Over Positivity</h2> <p>So what’s the solution here? Simple: stop pretending. Stop pretending everything is fine. Stop pretending like you’re not struggling. Be real. Embrace the mess. Let’s stop treating our emotions like problems to be “fixed” and start accepting them as part of the human condition. And when it comes to navigating this godforsaken world, authenticity is the best tool we’ve got. Maybe we won’t change the world overnight—but we’ll be better equipped to survive in it.</p> <p>And no, it doesn’t mean everything’s going to be okay. Even with this “solution”, there’s no guarantee you’ll end up with your happy ever after. But that’s life.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Because Toxic Positivity may be actually harming us]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflection: The Country Mouse Goes to New York</title><link href="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/mouse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection: The Country Mouse Goes to New York"/><published>2024-11-17T01:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-17T01:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/mouse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/mouse/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-country-mouse-goes-to-new-york">The Country Mouse Goes to New York</h2> <p>There’s a quaint little fable about the country mouse and the city mouse. You know, the one where the country mouse dreams of the city only to find it’s not all it’s cracked up to be—loud, overwhelming, and full of surprises. Having spent the last few years surrounded by Illinois’ endless cornfields, I thought I understood the country mouse. What I didn’t expect, though, was to <em>become</em> him during my trip to New York for the LIFEPLUS conference. Let’s just say the city had plans for me that involved cold weather, expensive food, and enough mishaps to fill an entire stand-up routine.</p> <h2 id="the-cornfield-mindset">The Cornfield Mindset</h2> <p>Champaign is…well, let’s call it “charmingly slow-paced.” Life here revolves around the basics: Walmart runs, the occasional splurge at Target, and more corn than you’ll ever know what to do with. I’ve spent plenty of time wishing for more—more things to do, more energy, more life. So when I was invited to attend the LIFEPLUS conference in New York City, I thought this was it. My <em>big moment</em>.</p> <p>I imagined myself effortlessly blending in with the hustle and bustle, soaking up the glamor and sophistication like a seasoned city dweller. What I got instead was a series of sobering reminders that I’m a country mouse through and through.</p> <h2 id="my-wallet-vs-the-city">My Wallet vs. the City</h2> <p>Let’s start with the pizza incident. I wanted a slice of quintessential New York—greasy, floppy, eaten while standing on a sidewalk. I’d watched enough Spider-Man movies to know that pizza was basically a prerequisite to being a real New Yorker, right up there with complaining about the weather and pretending to enjoy a crowded bar. Spoiler alert: reality? Not quite as glamorous as the movies made it seem. Or is it? I wouldn’t know.</p> <p>After squeezing through the bustling crowd, I found myself at <em>Joe G Pizza</em>, not to be confused with Joe’s Pizza, and ended up staring at a $30 menu and the mustache of a nice old Italian man, also named Joe. The pizza was 80% crust, 20% financial regret. If you’ve ever debated between two loaves of bread over a six-cent price difference, you’ll understand the kind of heartbreak I felt.</p> <p>And then there were the buses. Somehow, I managed to get off at the wrong stop <em>twice</em>. The first time, I waited over an hour in freezing cold for the next one, only to realize I was at the stop for buses heading in the opposite direction. The second time? Same story, but with extra frostbite. The only thing preventing me from being swallowed whole by the city’s chaos was the EDM Buddhist mantra I found myself singing(?) along to as night fell and my patience thinned. Om mani padme hum indeed.</p> <h2 id="the-lifeplus-conference-a-silver-lining">The LIFEPLUS Conference: A Silver Lining</h2> <p>Despite all the hiccups, the LIFEPLUS conference turned out to be everything I’d hoped for—and then some. Hanwha knows how to throw a party. There were live performances, endless trays of finger foods, and an open bar that made me feel like I’d stumbled into the VIP section of life. But the food? It wasn’t just food—it was an experience. I took a bite of caviar-infused hors d’oeuvres (French for “the good stuff”), and for a moment, I swear I felt my body’s net worth shoot up. The kind of luxurious taste that makes you question every budget meal you’ve ever eaten. Still, the real highlight (I swear!) came when I reconnected with people from my internship.</p> <p>Seeing them again reminded me that the world is good, and that maybe, just maybe, I should trust it more. I got to chat with new people, too—folks from different walks of life, sharing their stories in a way that felt safe and warm. Going to social meetups only to find people only talking to their little huddle of friends has taught me that it’s not every day you find a space where connecting with strangers feels natural, but this was one of those rare moments.</p> <p>Now, did I overindulge? Absolutely. Four cocktails, two glasses of wine, and half a bottle of beer later, my face was starting to swell up (thanks, alcohol intolerance). To be fair, my alcohol meter was topped up from the half-bottle of beer, the rest just went towards filling up my social battery for the night. But even through the haze of questionable decisions, I couldn’t help but smile. It was a good time. A really good time. Especially after two midterm exams and a final project out of the way.</p> <h2 id="the-squirrels-of-champaign">The Squirrels of Champaign</h2> <p>Still, as much as I loved the conference, I felt more at home walking down the quiet streets of Champaign. There’s something grounding about watching two squirrels chase each other through the trees or hearing the familiar crunch of gravel under your shoes.</p> <p>The city dazzles with its lights and promises of endless excitement, but it’s also exhausting. For someone like me—who finds joy in te weekly Aldi Finds, hesitates over splurging on eggs, and feels happiest surrounded by open skies and empty fields—home will always be where life moves a little slower.</p> <p>I may have ventured out of my comfort zone, but I came back with a deeper appreciation for what I have. The country mouse in me? He’s here to stay.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Because I prefer my plain food and simple life in the country]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflection: Art and the Search for Greener Grass</title><link href="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/art/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection: Art and the Search for Greener Grass"/><published>2024-10-08T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-08T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/art</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/art/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-dream-that-wasnt">The Dream That Wasn’t</h2> <p>In the quiet corners of my childhood, art was my secret portal to worlds unseen. With crayons in hand, I ventured into lands of imagination, sketching adventures where I battled mythical beasts and emerged a hero at the end of it all. Each stroke of color was a step into a universe where anything was possible—a place where my dreams took flight. Art wasn’t just a way to kill time; it was my language, my way of connecting with the world around me in a manner only a child could understand.</p> <p>Yet, as the years passed, whispers of doubt began to cloud the vibrant landscape. It didn’t take long before the vivid scenes I created were overshadowed by the looming shadows of practicality. The dream of becoming an artist and inviting others to my world quietly retreated into the background, replaced by the more “sensible” paths that adulthood seemed to demand. And without the courage or confidence to stand my ground, I could only watch as the treehouse of dreams was replaced with iron bars that drew a line across the horizon. The artist inside me was boxed up, sealed away, while the world told me it was time to “grow up” and “get real.”</p> <h2 id="get-in-the-fcking-robot">Get in the F*cking robot</h2> <p>Growing up doubting every decision, the world has a way of making choices for you. Computer science wasn’t a choice; it was an inevitability—society’s pre-packaged solution for the risk-averse. Wrapped in promises of stability and parental approval, I surrendered to it like a tired swimmer letting the current take them. And once I was in, there was no looking back, just more calculated moves forward. It felt safe. But in the background, there was always the nagging feeling that I wasn’t being brave enough to make my own choices. I wasn’t living; I was just existing in a box that someone else had drawn.</p> <p>I couldn’t trust myself to take big bets. While others chased dreams, I measured cliffs, calculating costs and multiplying anxieties until they became too large to ignore. The sensible path had been chosen, and I followed it, convincing myself that this was wisdom, not cowardice. I had become too good at rationalizing my own fears.</p> <h2 id="the-other-side">The Other Side</h2> <p>My internship at Hanwha was a turning point. Surrounded by people from diverse backgrounds, I met students who were fearlessly pursuing their dreams in their respective paths, including the arts. Not only did they have the proper background and talent to pursue what they wanted, they had the confidence and belief that they would be able to stick it out no matter the outcome. Their stories resonated with me, stirring memories of my own abandoned aspirations. Seeing them thrive in an environment that nurtured their passions made me reflect on what might have been if I had taken a similar leap of faith.</p> <p>Among these dreamers was a friend whose story could inspire a Hallmark movie. They moved abroad to attend an art high school in America, driven by a deep passion for creativity. Their journey was both inspiring and a bit bittersweet for me. Growing up, my family moved frequently, and each move felt like losing parts of myself—friendships, achievements, all left behind. But for them, moving was a sign of new beginnings, the start of something new and exciting. And although you could consider it to be a difference in perspective, I would argue that the difference between <em>choosing</em> to move and being forced to move without warning is something we can’t ignore.</p> <p>This realization got me thinking about the “what ifs.” What if I’d asked my family to move for my own artistic dreams? But I suppose a recent conversation with my family would answer that without a doubt—I remember an offhand comment about wanting majoring in the arts if I ever won the lottery, only to be met with laughter—a reminder of my reality where such dreams are mere punchlines. The contrast between my friend’s supportive environment and my own left me contemplating the paths not taken and dreams deferred, a painter who never found their canvas.</p> <h2 id="the-grass-we-water">The Grass We Water</h2> <p>But here’s the thing about looking over the fence: you miss the garden dying at your feet. I remember a time when I was so caught up in “what-ifs” that I nearly forgot to water my own plants. Literally. My poor houseplants were wilting while I daydreamed about alternate timelines where I’m someone I’m not and do things that, deep down, I know I would never do even if the opportunity came up. But reality has a way of snapping you back—like when you realize your once-thriving fern is now a crispy relic of negligence.</p> <p>It was then that I realized, maybe that’s okay. The imperfection part, not the houseplants. Maybe the point isn’t to bemoan the paths not taken, but to understand why we chose the ones we did. Sometimes, it’s easier to fantasize about being a different person than it is to embrace who you are and the decisions that led you here. Maybe the real challenge isn’t in wishing we were someone else—it’s in accepting who we are now and finding ways to bloom where we’re planted.</p> <p>I used to think the grass was always greener on the other side, but the truth is, it’s greener where you water it. If I spend too much time peering over the fence, I’ll never tend to the soil beneath me. That fern didn’t die because I wasn’t good enough; it died because I was too distracted, thinking about lives I wasn’t living. Maybe that’s the real lesson in all this—learning to stop fighting the person I am and start figuring out what that person needs to thrive.</p> <p>And this realization doesn’t just apply to career paths or artistic dreams—it applies to everything. Whether it’s relationships, goals, or passions, nothing will flourish unless we actively nurture it. The dream of being an artist may never have blossomed for me, but that doesn’t mean I can’t find fulfillment in other ways. I may have traded my crayons for a bunch of zeros and ones, but there’s still creativity in the logic, still room for growth in the unexpected places.</p> <p>So maybe the grass I once dreamed of is no longer the one I water. But that doesn’t mean I can’t make this garden beautiful, in my own way, with the tools I have.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Because we all look back once in a while]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflection: Working at Hanwha Finance</title><link href="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/hanwha/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection: Working at Hanwha Finance"/><published>2024-08-14T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-14T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/hanwha</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/hanwha/"><![CDATA[<p>My summer internship at Hanwha Finance was a whirlwind of experiences that left me both exhausted and exhilarated. As an AI data scientist, I found myself diving headfirst into the world of finance, armed with nothing but my wits and an unhealthy addiction to caffeine.</p> <h2 id="off-to-wonderland">Off to Wonderland</h2> <p>Diving into my project felt like slipping through the looking glass—everything around me was unfamiliar, a curious blend of ambition and industry. One of my proudest achievements during the internship was developing a Retrieval Augmented Generation (RAG) system tailored for the insurance domain. With barely any guidance (far less than I had expected, mind you), I threw myself headlong into crafting this tool. It became my digital sherpa, leading me through the dense jungle of financial literature, each paper a tangled thicket of jargon that would have otherwise been impenetrable.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0" style="max-width: 300px; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="font-size: 0.9rem; margin: 8px; line-height: 1.4;"> Captured my thoughts exactly </figcaption> </div> </div> <p>And where was this fantastical quest unfolding? In none other than the 63 Building, a towering monument of glass and steel that pierced the sky—one of Korea’s most iconic landmarks. It was as if I’d fallen into a different world, far removed from the sleepy lecture halls and cozy campus cafes back at university. Every morning felt like stepping through a portal. I’d stride through the lobby, polished floors gleaming beneath my feet, and into elevators that moved so fast they seemed to warp time itself. Somewhere between the 1st floor and the 60th, I stopped being a student and through some magical girl transformation, became someone who, at least in appearance, belonged among the sharp-suited professionals crowding the building. By the end of the internship, I’d almost convinced myself I wasn’t just pretending.</p> <p>The 63 Building wasn’t merely a place to work—it was a marvel, a skyscraper that felt like a dream made real. Outside, it stood tall among Seoul’s sprawling skyline, a giant in a city of giants, commanding attention. But inside, it was a world all its own. There was no wandering between classes or scribbling notes in some dingy lecture room. There was no looking out the window only to be greeted with the dancing cobs of corn for miles in every direction. This was the heart of the financial world, a place where decisions carried weight and everything buzzed with purpose. Each moment inside those walls carried a sense of urgency—an unspoken understanding that the stakes were higher here.</p> <p>The whole environment was intoxicating. The rapid pace, the hum of conversations blending with the tap-tap of keyboards, the almost-electric energy that lingered in the air—it felt like I was navigating a place where something monumental could happen at any moment. The building became my Wonderland, the elevator buttons my rabbit hole, each ascent revealing new challenges and possibilities. And push myself I did, day after day, until it felt like my brain was running on fumes, my thoughts spilling out like steam from a pressure valve.</p> <p>The further I ventured into this world, the more I felt the stark contrast with university life. Gone were the sleepy mornings where I’d drag myself to class with five minutes to spare. In this world of skyscrapers, time was a currency, and everyone seemed to be spending it wisely. It wasn’t just a job; it was an immersion, a reminder that beyond the cozy bubble of college life lay a much larger, more complex world. And somehow, against all odds, I was right in the middle of it, working at one of the tallest towers in the country—smack dab in the heart of it all.</p> <h2 id="the-meat-grinder-on-wheels">The Meat Grinder on Wheels</h2> <p><strong>Warning:</strong> The following paragraph contains vivid descriptions of public transportation chaos, sweat-soaked misery, and commuter survival tactics—proceed only if your spirit is strong and your stomach is steady.</p> <p>Of course, every adventure has its challenges. For me, it was the daily commute—a daily descent into what can only be described as a chaotic, flesh-pressing labyrinth of public transportation. Imagine this: the sweltering summer heat turning subway platforms into makeshift saunas, where the air felt thick enough to chew and every breath came with the distinct flavor of damp polyester and stress-induced sweat. Boarding the subway was less a matter of waiting for the doors to open and more like being willingly swallowed by a metal beast, squeezed between a wall of groggy salarymen and disheveled students, all locked together in a collective state of exhaustion and silent suffering.</p> <p>The buses were no better—every lurch and swerve transformed us into human pinballs, ricocheting off one another as the driver navigated Seoul’s streets with all the finesse of a rally racer late for his wedding. Clutching onto the nearest pole for dear life, I’d brace myself as the bus screeched through turns so sharp it felt like centrifugal force was actively trying to eject me out of the window. Between these death-defying stunts and the silent competition for seats (a sport that could rival Olympic-level wrestling), the bus rides were a battlefield in their own right.</p> <p>And if the subway and bus weren’t enough, the final leg of the journey required a 15-minute trek on foot, under the full glare of the unforgiving sun. The humidity clung to me like a second skin, and by the time I reached the office, I was usually drenched in sweat, with my shirt plastered to my back like a defeated flag of surrender. My shoes—once polished and pristine—now squeaked pitifully with each step, betraying the swamp that had formed inside. I’d walk into the lobby looking less like a finance professional and more like a survivor of some cruel, corporate Hunger Games.</p> <p>But in hindsight, even this daily grind added texture to the experience. It was the kind of suffering that, strangely enough, bonded me with the city itself—every stumble and sweat-soaked shirt becoming part of a larger story. And honestly, what’s an adventure without a bit of discomfort? Every scraped elbow from a subway turnstile, every bus ride where I was pinned against a window, and every uphill walk that left me gasping for breath became a strange badge of honor. It’s one thing to say you worked in a skyscraper like the 63 Building—it’s another to say you <em>survived</em> getting there.</p> <h2 id="the-city-of-yin-and-yang">The City of Yin and Yang</h2> <p>After long days wrestling with outdated documentation and pretending to understand all the financial gobblygook, I’d tumble out of the 63 Building and throw myself back into the commuter chaos, the metal beast of subways and buses, only to emerge in the electrifying pulse of Hongdae. Living there was like staying at the heart of a festival that never ended. The streets were a kaleidoscope of neon signs, booming music, and the irresistible scent of sizzling street food. Laughter and chatter filled the air, spilling from trendy cafes, night markets, and karaoke bars, as if the entire neighborhood had made a collective decision that sleep was overrated.</p> <p>Hongdae was a perfect blend of chaos and charm, the ultimate embodiment of yin and yang. By night, it was alive—no, <em>thriving</em>—a wild blur of color and sound. Every street felt like it was hosting its own block party, with buskers performing on corners, bars overflowing with young revelers, and the occasional DJ booth blasting bass-heavy beats into the open air. Every evening I wandered through this electric landscape to the coveted dormhouse, it felt like stepping into a dream I didn’t know I had—a life full of spontaneity and endless possibility, with every moment pulling me further from the spreadsheets and KPIs I’d left behind at the office.</p> <p>But mornings told a different story. As I trudged through the streets to catch the bus to work, the streets felt the eerie calm after a storm. The sidewalks, once so alive, were now scattered with the debris of last night’s revelry—empty bottles, cigarette butts, and the occasional lost pantyhose lying abandoned on the pavement. Storefronts were shuttered, and the streets were quiet, save for the low hum of delivery bikes cruising past and the rare elderly couple that seem to spawn randomly into existence once the youngins depart for the night. It was strangely beautiful, this sleepy, hungover version of Hongdae—a pocket of peace where everything stood still, waiting to be revived again after sunset.</p> <p>In those quiet mornings, the chaos of the night before felt nostalgic, like the aftermath of an unforgettable college party where you weren’t sure how the night ended, only that you had been part of something fleeting and meaningful. Walking through the remnants of last night’s fun, I felt oddly connected to the city and to the people who lived for those wild nights. It was as if Hongdae was offering two versions of itself—one that reminded me to embrace the vibrant madness, and another that allowed me to slow down and reflect, catching my breath before diving back into the whirlwind.</p> <p>This duality was mirrored in my own experience. Outside of work, I threw myself into Korea’s art scene as a way to reconnect with parts of myself I’d almost forgotten in the daily grind. I saw intimate theatre plays in dimly lit spaces, sat mesmerized at a musical, and found solace in jazz bars where the music wrapped around me like a warm blanket. And then there was the temple dedicated to the one and only Faker—a surreal, almost spiritual pit stop where I found myself praying for blessings on my next gacha pulls (because why not?). In those quiet moments, whether surrounded by jazz notes or aesthetic cafe walls, I felt like I was reclaiming pieces of my soul.</p> <p>Hongdae, with its dizzying nightlife and peaceful mornings, wasn’t just a place to stay—it was an experience, a reminder that life can be both thrilling and tranquil, chaotic and calm. And somehow, even after the craziest nights, the dormhouse always felt like home—a place to rest, reset, and get ready to do it all over again.</p> <h2 id="rediscovering-the-college-experience">Rediscovering the “College Experience”</h2> <p>The Global Internship Program (GIP) introduced me to people from across the world. We connected through shared experiences of studying abroad, collective love for Korean barbecue, and a soaked pattern at the back of our shirts at our arrival to the office. These interactions taught me a lot about people—and about myself (so much so that it deserves its own <a href="/blog/2024/art">post</a>).</p> <p>Ironically, it was only through this experience that I started to feel the magic of the “college experience” that people always talk about. Despite being a college student myself, I never quite felt like I was part of that vibrant, communal lifestyle. But this summer, working alongside peers who were just as ambitious and curious as me, I got a glimpse of what I’d been missing.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0" style="max-width: 400px; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-5-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-5-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-5-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-5.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="font-size: 0.9rem; margin: 8px; line-height: 1.4;"> Shoutout to our resident artist for this masterpiece of a farewell gift! Happy to contribute! </figcaption> </div> </div> <p>It felt like living out a coming-of-age movie—working hard, having fun, and building friendships that felt significant and meaningful rather than transactional. There was a shared sense of purpose, a common goal that brought us together. This was the life I’d always imagined I would live—being surrounded by talented, driven people, balancing work with meaningful connections, and growing not just as a professional, but as a person. All while trying not to pass out from the endless attack of business meetings.</p> <h2 id="the-royal-treatment-and-final-thoughts">The Royal Treatment and Final Thoughts</h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0" style="max-width: 200px; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="font-size: 0.9rem; margin-top: 8px; line-height: 1.4;"> <em>TL:</em> This accommodation is a restaurant, so dancing is <strong>strictly</strong> prohibited. Those that dance <strong>will</strong> be stopped. </figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Just when I thought I had a handle on this internship thing, the company threw us a curveball in the form of a beach trip. For a week, we worked on a consulting project during the day and bonded over horror movies and intense karaoke sessions at night. It was the kind of experience that turns colleagues into friends and projects into shared memories. I left with a tan, a newfound respect for one of the board executive’s singing ability, and the ability to finally be able to ride a wave as a San Diegan.</p> <p>Overall, the way Hanwha treated us interns exceeded all expectations. The week-long orientation felt more like a luxury retreat than corporate onboarding. We played team-building games that ranged from mildly embarrassing to downright ridiculous, ate fantastic food, and formed friendships and connections that will likely outlast the fleeting relevance of the latest social media trends.</p> <p>Looking back, my time at Hanwha Finance was a rollercoaster of learning, laughter, and mild heat exhaustion. It gave me new skills, unforgettable memories, and a deeper understanding of the kind of life I want to build—one filled with creativity, connection, and meaningful work. Would I do it all again? In a heartbeat. Just maybe with a bit more deodorant next time.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0" style="max-width: 500px; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-4-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-4-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-4-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/hanwha/hanwha-4.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figcaption style="font-size: 0.9rem; margin-top: 8px; line-height: 1.4;"> Always Remember. </figcaption> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Because the breaks are there for a reason]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflection: Working at the Illinois Leadership Center</title><link href="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/ilc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection: Working at the Illinois Leadership Center"/><published>2024-05-11T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-11T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/ilc</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jeybird248.github.io/blog/2024/ilc/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ilc/ilc-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ilc/ilc-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ilc/ilc-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/ilc/ilc.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>I stumbled into the Illinois Leadership Center on a sweltering August afternoon, my laptop bag slung over one shoulder and the weight of a disastrous freshman year on the other. The air conditioning hit me like a wave of relief, both from the heat and from the gnawing fear that I’d made a terrible mistake coming to UIUC. Little did I know, I was about to embark on a year-long adventure that would change everything.</p> <h3 id="the-maze-of-self-discovery">The Maze of Self-Discovery</h3> <p>Finding my way to the ILC office in the Illini Union was like navigating a labyrinth designed by some sadistic architect with a fetish for beige walls and identical corridors. It didn’t help that the building had two stairs to the second floor, where the ILC office was, each with their disjoint sets of rooms you could access from each entrance. By the time I finally reached the right door, I was convinced I’d aged at least three years and possibly grown a beard.</p> <p><em>“You must be the new data analyst,”</em> chirped a voice that was far too cheerful for 2 PM on a Monday. I turned to see a staff member with a smile so bright it could power a small city.</p> <p><em>“Welcome to the ILC!”</em></p> <p>I mumbled something that vaguely resembled English and followed them into what looked like the lovechild of a tech startup and a self-help seminar. Motivational posters plastered the walls, and I swear I could smell the faint aroma of freshly sharpened pencils and crushed dreams.</p> <h3 id="the-great-data-disappointment">The Great Data Disappointment</h3> <p>Now, let me tell you, I came into this gig thinking I was about to become the next big data wizard. I had visions of coding elaborate algorithms, creating AI models that could predict leadership potential based on how many times someone used the word <em>“synergy”</em> in a sentence.</p> <p>Reality, as it turns out, had other plans.</p> <p><em>“So, here’s where you’ll be making our reports,”</em> my supervisor explained, gesturing to a computer that looked like it had witnessed the birth of the internet. <em>“We need you to take all this workshop data and turn it into pretty pictures that will make even the most jaded administrator weep with joy.”</em></p> <p>I blinked. <em>“That’s it? Just… making reports?”</em></p> <p>He nodded, oblivious to my internal existential crisis. <em>“Yep! It’s crucial work. We need to show the impact of our programs.”</em></p> <p>And just like that, my dreams of data sorcery crumbled into a pile of pie charts and bar graphs.</p> <h3 id="the-human-element">The Human Element</h3> <p>But here’s the kicker – amidst all the report-making monotony, I found something I wasn’t expecting: human connection.</p> <p>Coming off a freshman year where I’d managed to surround myself with the wrong crowd and henceforth set my personal relationships blazing aflame faster than you can say <em>“Burn my Bread,”</em> I was more than a little wary of people. Yet, somehow, the ILC became my sanctuary.</p> <p>My supervisor, a beacon of calm in my storm of self-doubt, always seemed to materialize with a pep talk just when I was on the verge of a data-induced breakdown. And my two coworkers? They became my partners in crime, turning mundane tasks into opportunities for inside jokes and shared eye-rolls at particularly “enthusiastic” workshop participants.</p> <p>For the first time in what felt like forever, I looked forward to coming to work. It wasn’t about the data anymore; it was about the people.</p> <h3 id="the-leadership-revelation">The Leadership Revelation</h3> <p>As I immersed myself in the world of leadership workshops and development programs, something unexpected happened.</p> <p>My cynical view of leadership – you know, the one where I imagined all leaders as cigar-chomping fat cats making decisions from their ivory towers – began to crumble. I watched as students grappled with concepts like emotional intelligence, inclusive leadership, and ethical decision-making.</p> <p>I saw them struggle, grow, and emerge with a new understanding of themselves and their potential impact on the world. And somewhere along the way, I realized that leadership wasn’t about being the boss or having all the answers. It was about empowering others, about creating environments where people could thrive, about making tough decisions with integrity.</p> <p>It was, I realized with a jolt, about everything the ILC had been quietly doing for me all along.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ilc/urs-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ilc/urs-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ilc/urs-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/ilc/urs.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="the-bittersweet-end">The Bittersweet End</h3> <p>As my year at the ILC drew to a close, I looked back on the mountains of reports I’d generated, the forests of charts I’d cultivated, and the oceans of coffee I’d consumed.</p> <p>I’d come in as a number-cruncher and was leaving as… well, still a number-cruncher, but one with a newfound appreciation for the human side of leadership.</p> <p>The ILC had given me more than just a job. It had given me a community, a purpose, and yet another way I could judge people’s character off of.</p> <p>As I packed up my trusty laptop and said goodbye to my data-driven domain, I couldn’t help but feel a little misty-eyed. After all, how many people can say they’ve quantified the journey to self-discovery? How many have graphed the path to enlightenment or calculated the ROI on empathy?</p> <p>As I stepped out into the warm Illinois sun, I realized that my time at the ILC had been more than just a job – it had been a leadership lab of my own. And I had emerged as the ultimate data point: transformed, inspired, and only slightly over-caffeinated.</p> <p>Now, if you’ll excuse me, I have a sudden urge to go facilitate a workshop on <em>“Data Visualization as a Path to Self-Actualization.”</em> I hear the ILC has an opening.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Because we all take the first step eventually]]></summary></entry></feed>